Alfred Freedman MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
- Writings, Original writings and printed materials from Dr. Freedman can be found in this series.
  - Lawsuits regarding manuscripts correspondence, KFS Associates certificate of incorporation, agreements, notes, and memos, 1969 - 1971; 1973 - 1975; 1977; 1979 - 1982; 1987; undated; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - “Almost Fifty Years in Psychopharmacology: A Memoir” for Collegium Internationale Neuro-Psychopharmacologicum with correspondence, photographs, and the International Photo Archives in Neuropsychopharmacology booklet and compact disc, 1989; 1999 - 2000; undated (Box 13)
  - “A proposal for an international study of commitment of the mentally ill”, undated (Box 14)
  - “To the benefit of psychiatric patients” presentation at the Japanese Society of Psychiatry and Neurology in Kyoto, Japan, 1987 (Box 14)
  - “A model for teaching according to the biopsychosocial model” presentation at the Third Pacific Rim College of Psychiatrists in Tokyo, Japan, 1986 (Box 14)
  - “A paradigm of urban blight: adolescent narcotic addiction” presentation at the Annual Meeting of the New York State Recreation Society in Syracuse, New York, 1961 (Box 14)
  - “Narcotic addiction: the middle range outlook” presentation at the American College of Neuropsychopharmacology in San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1972 (Box 14)
  - “Pharmacologic assessment of narcotic antagonists” with Richard B. Resnick, 1973 (Box 14)
  - “Studies of en-1639a (naltrexone) a new narcotic antagonist” with Richard B. Resnick, Jan Volavka, Thelma Jones, and Muriel Thomas, 1973 (Box 14)
  - “High dose cyclazocine therapy of opiate dependence” with Richard B. Resnick and Max Fink, 1973 (Box 14)
  - “Naloxone pamoate: a long-acting opiate antagonist” with Robert Levine, Arthur Zaks, and Max Fink, undated (Box 14)
  - “Treatment of heroin dependence with opiate antagonists” with Richard B. Resnick, Max Fink, and Arthur Zaks, 1969 (Box 14)
  - “A comparison of drug users and non-users among affluent high school youth” with Richard Brotman, Irving Silverman, and Fred Suffet, 1968 (Box 14)
  - “The role of NGO’s in psychiatric education in developing countries” presentation at the WHO workshop on international collaboration in postgraduate education in London, England, 1986 (Box 14)
  - “Children under fire” presentation at the Conference on Aspects of Psychiatric Problems of Childhood and Adolescence in Paris, France, 1979 (Box 14)
  - “Depression in the physically ill with a grave prognosis” presentation at the Meeting of the International Committee for Prevention and Treatment of Depression in St. Moritz, Switzerland, 1983 (Box 14)
  - “Teaching and research in the general hospital”, undated (Box 14)
  - “Ethics of deinstitutionalization in the USA” presentation at Fukuoka University School of Medicine in Fukuoka, Japan, 1986 (Box 14)
  - “A contemporary view of psychiatric education in the USA” presentation at Fukuoka University School of Medicine in Fukuoka, Japan and in Jakarta, Indonesia, 1986; 1988 (Box 14)
  - “Present and future trends in psychiatric education” presentation at the World Psychiatric Association in Kyoto, Japan, 1982 (Box 14)
  - “The content of the education of a psychiatrist” presentation at the World Psychiatric Association in Madrid, Spain, 1980 (Box 14)
  - “Medical education for the next seventeen years” presentation at the VII World Congress of Psychiatry in Vienna, Austria, 1983 (Box 14)
  - “The combined therapy for depression: a review and guide for the general practitioner” presentation at the World Psychiatric Association in Athens, Greece, 1985 (Box 14)
  - “Law and psychiatry: the future and its challenges” presentation at the International Academy of Law and Mental Health in Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1987 (Box 14)
  - “Aspects of schizophrenia” presentation at the World Psychiatric Association in Moscow, Russia, 1973 (Box 14)
  - “Justice and fairness in psychiatric commitment” presentation at the Fondation Internationale des Sciences Humaines in Vienna, Austria, 1978 (Box 14)
  - “Psychopharmacology and psychotherapy in the treatment of anxiety”, undated (Box 14)
  - “Guidelines for the treatment of anxiety disorders”, undated (Box 14)
  - “Setting back psychiatry: a critique of the report of the UN subcommission on prevention of discrimination and protection of minorities the DAES report” presentation at the World Psychiatric Association in Copenhagen, Denmark, 1986 (Box 14)
- Correspondence, Dr. Freedman’s professional correspondence is in this series.
  - New York Medical College faculty, 1969 - 1970; 1972 - 1978; 1980; 1983; undated (Box 14)
  - Personal and retirement, 1988; undated (Box 14)
  - New York Times, 2010 (Box 14)
  - Hanfried Helmchen, including photographs and research on incompetent mental patients, 1997 - 1998; 2001 - 2004 (Box 14)
  - Michael Schwartz, philosophy and phenomenology, 2000; 2002 - 2003 (Box 15)
  - Leon Eisenberg, 2000 - 2004 (Box 15)
  - Driss Moussaoui, 2000 - 2003; 2005 (Box 15)
  - Abraham Halpern, 2000 - 2004; undated (Box 15)
  - Costas Stefanis tribute volume, 1999 - 2000 (Box 15)
  - Pierre Pichot, 1999 - 2003 (Box 15)
  - Mary Ann Cohen, 1996; 1998 - 2001 (Box 15)
  - Masahisa Nishizono, 1996; 2000 - 2005 (Box 15)
  - Emeritus, 1995; 1997 - 2005; undated (Box 15)
- Photographs, This contains photographs from Dr. Freedman’s life and work, particularly at academic conferences.
  - American Psychiatric Association past presidents luncheon, 1991 - 1992; 1994; 1998 (Box 15)
  - American Psychiatric Association annual meetings in Anaheim, California and New Orleans, Louisiana, 1975; 1981 (Box 15)
  - American Psychiatric Association board of trustees, 2000 - 2001; 2004 (Box 15)
  - Dr. Freedman in Greece, c. 1985 (Box 15)
  - Portrait photographs, 1967; undated (Box 15)
  - New York Medical College campus, logo, and convocation, 1988; undated (Box 15)
  - Family, 1983; undated (Box 15)
- Memorabilia, This series primarily has certificates documenting Dr. Freedman’s awards and leadership.
  - Office of the County Executive, Westchester County, New York certificate of appreciation, 1985 (Box 15)
  - American Psychiatric Foundation membership for president’s club, 1994 (Box 15)
  - American Psychiatric Association certificates of commendation for chairing task force to plan a joint meeting with the French, chairing ad hoc committee on the key conference recommendations, chairing the nominating committee, distinguished life fellow, and 50 years of service, 1976; 1978; 2001; 2003 (Box 15)
  - New York Medical College Terence Cardinal Cooke Medal for Distinguished Service in Health Care, 1985 (Box 15)
  - American Orthopsychiatric Association life fellow certificate, 1979 (Box 15)
  - American Psychopathological Association membership certificate, 1967 (Box 15)
  - University of Minnesota Bachelor of Medicine diploma, 1941 (Box 15)
  - World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry regional congress participation certificate, 1990 (Box 15)
  - William Alanson White Institute of Psychiatry, Psychoanalysis, and Psychology certificate in psychoanalysis, 1956 (Box 15)
  - American Academy of Child Psychiatry fellow certificate, 1958 (Box 15)
  - Veterans Administration Medical Center Deans Committee service award certificate, 1985 (Box 15)
  - Alpha Xi University of Minnesota chapter of Phi Delta Epsilon Fraternity and Phi Kappa Phi Cornell University honor society chapter certificates, 1936; 1938 (Box 15)
  - Harlem Hospital intern rotating service diploma, 1942 (Box 15)
  - Hunan Medical University honorary professor appointment certificate, undated (Box 15)
  - Army of the United States certificate of service, 1946 (Box 15)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science fellow and fifty year member certificates, 1958; 1997 (Box 15)
  - Ellis Island Foundation official certificates of registration in American immigrant wall of honor for Jacob Abraham Freedman and Pauline Hoffman Freedman, undated (Box 15)
  - Lenox Hill Hospital certificate of appreciation, 1995 (Box 15)
  - Academy of Psychoanalysis fellow certificate, 1956 (Box 15)
  - Mount Sinai Hospital resident in pathology certificate, 1946 (Box 15)
  - Medical Society of the State of New York citation for fifty years of service certificate, 1991 (Box 15)
  - Program and speeches for gathering in memory of Helen Zunser Wortis, 1976 (Box 15)